hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
iding Our Guest today is Kenneth
schlanker founder and CEO at opal a
screen time app with a mission to
empower humans to focus better every day
on the podcast we talk with Kenneth
about scaling to 5 million in ARR on
paid ads positive and negative results
from
121 AB tests and why they still have
build an Android app hey Kenne thanks so
much for joining us on the podcast today
thanks so much for having me David very
excited to be here and Jacob nice to
have you joining us today as well I'm
excited to talk about screen time and
limiting it with opal today so let's go
Kenneth I wanted to kick things off
talking about opal I'd love for you to
share just what the app is and why you
created it sure yeah opal is a screen
time app available on the App Store we
today are the leading application for
screen time management and and yeah it's
an app that basically saves you an
average of an hour and 20 minutes per
day in less screen time and helps you be
more balanced in how you use your phone
awesome so I know you've been thinking
about building opal in this
3phase approach and I think that this
approach is something a lot of apps
should consider is that when you first
launch there's certain things you should
be thinking about and then as you kind
of move along you change focus and grow
so let's talk through those different
phases of how you think about opal and
how to grow it as a subscription app
Business what's the first phase and kind
of how you kicked off launching and
finding product Market fit with opal
we've been at this for three years now
and started off with just thinking that
there's an opportunity to build better
screen time software than what's
available by default on every single
iPhone and actually Android today but we
did this in phases that you said the
first phase was really about okay let's
prove the opportunity not only that
people are willing to use a better
screen time software but also that
they're willing to pay for it and we've
been in that phase for over two and a
half years so it's a long journey you
know in this first phase the main metric
of success for us has been d8 return at
spend so essentially what we try to
figure out is not only are people
willing to use an app but are they
willing to pay for it and then are we
able to acquire customers in a way that
makes sense economically with just
immediate cash payback and you shared
with me before that y'all hit 5 million
in ARR which is an incredible milestone
for a subscription app and I would have
thought three years ago in your founding
like oh we're going to build a screen
time app ah it's built into iOS do
people really need it are people really
going to pay for it I'm sure you never
heard that Kenneth in your it's first
time in that first phase like how did
you think about proving out whether or
not people actually care enough to use
and pay for and can you build an app
that like is a better version of what
comes for free in the system I think
something amazing about subscriptions
and obviously this is music to your ears
at Revenue cat but something amazing in
this early stage of the business is that
essentially if you get people to pay for
your products as a consumer that's a
pretty strong signal that you have
something that's pretty valuable and so
there used to be a sort of trend of
consumer apps that well okay let's build
a use case let's get people to use this
and then we'll figure out how to
monetize later but actually we took it
the other way around which is let's
build something that's good enough for
people to pay for it first let's figure
out who these people are let's figure
out how we can actually acquire people
like these people specifically and
that's sort of the original product
Market fit you mentioned we recently
passed yeah 5 million in AR we basically
did this in a year starting from almost
zero a year ago to 5 million just
recently and this has been done with
basically focusing relentlessly on how
can we build something that people are
willing to pay for and then figuring out
who those people are and figureing out
how to acquire more of these people and
you know specifically for us what's
interesting Is We I actually initially
launched a business thinking well this
app will be used mostly by I would say
you like genz kind of younger maybe
students but it turned out that the
people willing to pay for the app are
more sort of knowledge workers 25 to 40
who care about this issue so much
they're willing to pay for it and they
kind of also see direct Roi of the time
they're saving how they can actually be
more productive at work spend more time
outside of work with their family for
example and so it's been a really
interesting way to essentially use
subscription as discovery engine as a
product Market fit engine just focusing
on this one metric which is d8 return
out span I'm curious in those early days
I don't stare at everybody's stuff but
once in a while I'll see somebody pop to
the top of a leaderboard and last year
I've seen opal be like oh you guys
figured something out right in those
early days as you were like iterating on
Ras were you dumping money in from the
very beginning and like how much like
how did that practically work because
you kind of need some amount of critical
mass to make those measurements and did
you do that literally on day one was
there no like period of no monetization
just like experimentation or how did
that play out there was an MVP phase
which was just getting the product to
work which mostly test flight only a few
hundred people but immediately once we
were on the App Store we immediately
started testing paid marketing and so
basically with a pay wall and I think we
hooked up Revenue cats from the very
first week that's when we met yeah yeah
on the App Store and yeah it gave us a
lot of signal really fast gave us volume
you know I think in the early days what
you want is you want 100 downloads
consistently per day more than like you
know drip of like a thousand downloads
on a weit list so having a drip of 100
people per day paid marketing can
actually deliver that quite well and
then you're able to push a new release
every single week one thing we've done
also from the very first week that we
were on the App Store until today is
we've released one app version every
single week on Monday that's really sort
of a discipline in the team that creates
a rhythm where you can actually
experiment things and by Thursday you're
like let's get something in because I
want to see the number change you know
the next week right yeah right and then
sometimes it's a very small thing
sometimes it's much bigger but that
allows us to organize our work around
this really cycle and it aligns really
well with we look at day eight Ras
because we have a one week free trial
and the big advantage of that is you get
like very short duration cycle so if you
make something new on Monday eight days
later you get a sense of like did you
get an increase or decrease in Ras and
you can keep iterating with very short
Cycles so that's yeah I think it's a
really good way to discover the True
Value what you're building I also think
you know the landscape changed so much
in like the last few years I mean what
was true of three or four years ago is
not the case today and today it's much
harder to break through organically as
an app maker and many people do it I
don't know necessarily how to do it so
for me it was okay you let's figure out
something that people willing to pay for
that we can actually acquire customers
for and now we're thinking we're kind of
going going the opposite way of thinking
okay like how do we actually from here
now build a lot more organic traction
did you have specific milestones in
those early days like we're going to
launch and we're okay for now as a
learning at 50% day eight row as or 25%
and was that the case I mean when you
first started spending on ads was it
like 20% row outs at day eight so you
knew you were going to spend money to
learn and then it just kind of inched
toward that 100% or how did that go
early on we spent a very small amount of
money in the early days as a test
but very soon we reached 100% Ras I mean
part of the reason for that is we priced
quite high from the beginning it's $100
subscription on annual basis when we
start off actually we're at 69 and we
ended up like Rising the price but
throughout this past year we went from
zero to 5 million in AR we've been
operating at over 100% day eight or as
so basically we don't have a marketing
budget like we're only reinvesting with
8 day cycle I think the point you make
about using 8 day how much money you
realize Revenue in 8 days over ad spend
is really smart the subscription model
has enough like inputs and variables
that it can tend to get confusing even I
think for the smartest people to totally
reason about and so I think it's really
helpful to cut and slice something that
you believe is going to be indicative
and optimize you know what you were
saying better for that iteration cycle
than total correctness right you're
going to be wrong sometimes like you're
probably going to overspend probably
some of those cohorts weren't fully
positive based on measurements and
whatever but as long as you have some
number that you believe in the grand Arc
is going to relate to your goal reducing
that measurement time is the most
important and then you couple that with
a rapid iteration cycle that's rocket
fuel right just keep hitting it and
hitting it and hitting it and hitting it
until you're where you want to be but
it's interesting you know definitely get
super confusing I mean the main value
for me is like having one metric that
you look at is like it's hard enough for
the CEO and you got to communicate it to
a bunch of people right that aren't as
familiar with the model and all that
stuff but honestly it's enough even just
for you right the product's complicated
enough don't make the business model
super complicated too you know yeah that
was a good learning of like just Pi one
metric that you can iterate against it's
just simplifies so much I mean I
wouldn't say we didn't get there right
away like by the way what I'm talking
about right now is like this clear one
phase where we only did date R it didn't
actually happen like that from the
beginning it evolved into that and
decided to drop everything else and just
focus on this single metric but once we
did that's really when we were able to
grow yeah I think folks like think they
have to build a whole company first
right you don't you just got to get one
little engine of something going right
and forget about all the other things
forget about tackling too much and the
reason that that's okay is you will need
to do all those other things but it's
much easier at 5 million in ARR than it
is at zero you just have a little more
resources you have a little more
attention you have a little more
experience so did you just stick with
like the tiny little drips of AD spend
and then one day you're like okay let's
go and then just turn the money on how
did you decide and then what was that
like to trigger the infliction we tested
until we got close to we didn't get to
100 right away when we start scaling but
we felt like we had a path to get to
100% and that's when we started to scale
at spend and then basically we pilot at
spend based on that like every week we
look at what was the you know Ras the
previous week are we able to expand
budgets or have to lower them if we're
below 100% we just basically cut back to
get back to 100% And yeah week over week
basically driving that Evolution as long
as we're above 100% we scale so that's
how we started spending a lot more and
then we're able to grow there's no like
Grove goal that comes from like just I
want to get to 5 million it just like
happens as a consequence of setting the
bar in terms of overas tactically how
were you measuring that so were you just
doing Blended return on ad spend from a
weekly cohort so you would just say
everybody who opened the app during this
week counts towards our spend that week
what's the ACT ual calculation of day
eight row as yeah so now we look at
cohorted based on install so someone who
installs the app within that week and
then we look at the revenue that
generate 8 days from install we also
look at day 30 when we started out it
was much Slimer than that we just looked
at how much are we spending this week
and how much are we making a week later
with a eight day delay that's sort of
works you know at the beginning and then
you end up at a point where you have a
lot of like late conversion so people
download the app in January and end up
paying in May and then so the numbers
don't line up and so you need to have a
cohorted view but we started off in the
most basic way possible the other thing
we do is we do attribution in a very
simple way which is we ask people on the
on boarding where they came from and we
found that to be actually the most
reliable way of doing it so I mean we
also have like all the fancy like
attribution software and at the end of
the day just asking people you know
where they heard about us and if they
say Facebook it's one thing and they say
Word of Mouth something else and then
basically you segments the cohort based
on that answer and then we look at
unblended roas based on those cohorts
another good example of keeping it
simple you could tie yourself in a knot
being like well not everybody that
installed that week probably saw an ad
that week they probably saw it the week
before or whatever and then like
suddenly you're tied up all in your cord
and you're falling over or you just go
like yeah I don't know we'll just say
everybody who installed this week saw an
ad this week right and it's like is it
correct no but is it useful probably and
it lets you make decisions faster you
know it's funny I mean I should probably
talk to you guys more about this is you
probably have a ton of experience
working with other apps but attribution
is one of the things I talk to other app
Founders most about like how do you guys
do this what are the best practices
everybody has a different view there's
not like one single fully approved
method for doing this so there's
everybody's doing their but yeah I
thought it's just asking people where
they come from is just the dumbest but
also the probably most reliable way of
doing it you know even if you had
perfect instrumentation on every single
campaign and every single creative and
all that stuff you probably as a team
your size don't have the time to action
on all of that data anyway right so you
have to kind of think in Broad terms
like how much are we spending on this
channel on this broad creative strategy
you know so I mean I guess falling off
of that I sent you an email the other
week because I got an ad on Instagram
for opal that was so good which like
maybe talk about that so you talk about
spend and campaigns and stuff but
there's like the whole building the
creative and like all of that stuff how
are you splitting your time between app
development the performance actual
marketing and putting those things out
there and then like the creative
development part thank you for that
feedback I loved receiving your email
yeah it's basically for people who
haven't seen it maybe you have but we
did release an ad actually a few weeks
ago that took over our entire campaigns
and basically this ad it's much more of
a organic type video that talks about
our mission in general more than the it
doesn't even show the product yeah was
so good though I was like I was like
amped up it was like 1984 like the
famous Apple ad it was great we'll link
it in the show notes there's a fun story
also about this what happen happened is
someone made this video before we ever
reached out to them and it wasn't about
opal it was just about the space but we
like to talk to creators who are
sensitive to the mission that we have
and it was very align ra mission right
so we reached out to them and they wrote
back and said actually I use opal and I
love it we're like well can we use this
video as an ad and they said yeah sure
you should just take it and we made a
deal with them we tweaked it slightly
but really it was made as organic
content and worked really really well
and actually now we have more it was the
second time we're doing this wasn't the
first time but now we're doing this a
lot more where we're finding that
basically whenever we talk about the
mission it's working quite well so it's
probably 80% of the work is creative 20%
is sort of campaign management
performance so definitely creative is
play a big part we've tried everything
we have tried several agencies where
including like fully outsourced creative
agencies that basically like make ads
will run it for you and you pay a
percent of spend we've tried working
just with creative agencies that just
send us Concepts and we're more and more
doing things fully inous with I mean
Lally right now it's seem of one and
then a little bit of Contracting what
we're finding works right now is finding
creators in our space that like care
about what we're doing ideally they
using the app and they love it and then
producing stuff with them but I mean in
terms of like spending my time I
actually have someone great in the team
right now like that's really
specifically creative Partnerships
manager who's working just on the
creative side and we're looking to bring
someone else with more the sort of
typical user acquisition I would say
more sort of technical side of campaign
management and data we're a team of
seven we have one person that just does
creatives basically speaking from CEO
position the folks that come in and
they're most excited about Revenue cat
in our mission they bring a certain
Something Magic that is hard to find and
bring that in in your creative work and
and that's one of the reasons with the
exception of a few Fringe activities
like I don't love working with
contractors especially for core things
right and for an app Business the market
marketing is very core it maybe is
marketing it's maybe not part of the
product technically but as a founder and
a builder it is right this is probably
half of what you're focused on all the
time is like the acquisition aspect
definitely I think it's probably half
products half marketing would be a good
spit of my time and it's interesting
because yeah marketing informs product
product informs marketing it really kind
of works together we have to understand
why people are willing to pay inside the
app like what features so for example
one of the things that people love is
the ability to essentially like lock
yourself out of distracting app without
any way of canceling or bypassing the
normal I know I dismiss I dismiss screen
time every day I'm like goodbye computer
I have power over you ignore all day so
we for you Jacob have built this special
feature it's called deep focus and
basically there's no way to cancel our
bypass that's just simple you know value
proposition this is one of the reasons
why people like this app and like to pay
for it and so of course you want to
build creative around that and that
tends to work well just like you know
understanding why are people using this
for work during the day or they using it
in the evening to kind of Disconnect and
unplug with family or with friends like
what's the use case that you can
highlight in ads and then also when you
see an ad or creative that works that
talks about I don't know sleep for
example you're like well actually maybe
we should make a bigger deal of sleep
inside the product and prove the product
so it kind of works both ways and it's I
would say probably 50/50 right now of
like my time and attention between
product and marketing well we could talk
about this for another hour the zero to
one stuff is so fascinating and all the
ads up but I did want to move on to the
second phase that you're now moving into
after getting this dialed in and that's
the fremium strategy so tell me about
why you decided that this was a needed
second phase to move into as a company
so we believe that there needs to be
great screen time software available for
everyone we think focus is very
important in the 21st century and what
that means is like we don't really have
I think the luxury of being like a
smaller Niche product by n i mean it
could be a very profitable business with
like a few hundred thousand people they
are subscribed or but we really think
that this product we're building needs
to be used by millions of people one of
the things we see is students for
example right like we get a huge amount
of organic traction with students but
the business model we have right now is
focused on converting people to a pretty
expensive yearly plan that doesn't fit
at all this audience like very few
students at scale I think will pay $99 a
year but there's a huge amount of
fraction they really really need it and
I'm going to say students I mean college
but also it goes down to junor high
school high school the mission for us is
very important and so we'd like to get
in the hands of people who need it and
there's probably millions of them so we
don't think we have a choice to kind of
stay just smaller and the second phase
that we're entering is about building
the best screen time app for all
knowledge workers all students and in a
way that allows them to use a daily for
free and that means we need to build a
better premium funnel smarter upsells
most of what we done the first phase
where we focused on day eight Ras was
about converting people right away onto
a payall or they pay an annual plan
mostly I would say like based on
intention I would call this the gym
membership effect where you're going in
you want to change and so you're paying
for an expensive subscription not only
because you want access the gym but also
because you want to change and make a
commitment to yourself so that's worked
really well in the first phase but in
the second phase we're moving away from
this and building a more premium funnel
where you can start to use the product
for free do a lot of things and then
like there's different ways in which you
pay for the app subscriptions and also
you know in app payments I would say
like smarter upsells so we're kind of
doing maybe the opposite of what for
example dualingo did where you know they
started off completely free focusing on
retention and then figured out okay like
how do we actually get people to pay
we're doing the opposite which is we
figured out how to get people to pay a
smaller number but now we're looking at
how do we expand this to many many more
people including people using it for
free right now the paid penetration so
if you look at the monthly actives of
opal 177% are paid subscribers and I
think if you compare that to dualingo
for example they're 78% paid penetration
so you know what that means is we can
probably have a lot more people using
the product for free and convert a
smaller percentage of people while still
having a great business why do I think
it's necessary also to have a premium
funnel to grow much faster I think it
comes down to it's just a lot easier to
talk to your friends about an app if
it's a free app than if it's a paid app
I think lingo onboarding says learn a
language for free forever that's like on
the onboarding for a screen I think that
the perception even though actually
their app isn't really free I mean
there's a lot of paid features but like
the perception as a free app is so
important in organic referrals and so
yeah that's what we're working on in the
second phase and the other aspect is
when I look around at other subscription
businesses and maybe have more examples
of this but I think there's many
subscription apps that kind of hit a
ceiling at maybe 10 maybe 20 sometimes
30 million doar in AR and they end up
with a model where they can be dependent
on paid advertising mostly converting
people in the onboarding and it's really
hard to break the seiling we want to
avoid the seating by working on it now
essentially if you scaled the RAS
eventually you will have attracted all
of the available people you can attract
you can localize and things like this
but eventually your churn and your
acquisition will reach an equilibrium
probably around in that range it is
fascinating to see the DU lingo move
reversed right and also has to do
capitalization because dualingo raised a
ton of money to basically run
unprofitably for a long time before they
finally and then they did turn on a big
money machine which is the bet but it's
interesting to see a more Capital
efficient probably way of doing this
which is starting from this position and
widening out one thing I'm curi say was
it going to be to be able to maintain
you come in it's a premium product it's
a gym for Millennial knowledge workers
but then also like that same app has to
communicate to the 19-year-old freshman
in College who's just trying to like
Focus for their midterm I think it's
hard the way I look at it is like this
phase one we pass level one right now
like passing level two it's just as hard
to pass this level two I mean the
conviction we have is that if you look
at dingo right it's like they were able
to democratize learning language make it
fun and make it like a game we think
like the ability to focus it's not just
screen time management but it's about
like learning to focus is something that
is just as big and maybe even bigger in
terms of like how many people need to
use this learning a language is a real
luxury good you know what I mean like
you only do that if you have a lot of
time and like you maybe have aspirations
to travel and things like this but I
feel like screen time is something that
plagues everybody right yeah that's the
bet and so I think even if it's hard we
have this conviction that it's really
Mass Market a lot of people that could
use this and so the tricky part is what
we did so the first phase was simple
like day eight oras is the main goal
right the main metric phase two is a
little bit more complex we look at
retention of course as a main metric
whether people pay or not like just how
many people are still using yeah usage
and then the second thing is arpu we
want to make sure that we can increase
retention while having an arpu which is
lower than it was before but doesn't go
below a certain level so basically we
have those numbers and it's if we can
increase retention where we want it to
be and then reduce our arpu you know the
first year to above $2 we can change the
trajectory of the business massively and
actually we've done some of it already
so you know one the things we did for
example is make it easier to dismiss the
original onboarding pay wall so that
more people start using the app and more
people start using the free version of
the app and we were able to do this in a
way that increased activation and
decreased arpu in a way that's
manageable so basically like the net is
positive in the long run that's the way
we calculate so like if you can make
those bets remove a little bit of
friction for payments early and then
that increases retention and then make
sure that it doesn't destroy rpu too
much and if you can have those two work
together I think that's the key it's a
fun example and just evolving your model
a little bit which I found I've had to
do it several times at Revenue cat like
every year and sometimes you forget and
then like you wake up one day and you're
like the numbers I'm supposed to be
caring about don't really represent what
I care about anymore and you have to go
back and You' be like okay actually
these are the numbers we care about you
have to sort of recast the business in a
new set of metrics and it's good I mean
that's the right way to do it it's like
think about that first think about what
you're trying to do state your
hypothesis right then state how you're
going to measure it then go do things
that's the real scientific method so
yeah it's so interesting that you also
come across I think it's fascinating to
do this and speaking of like how you
spend your time as a CEO and like what
you focus on definitely the more you can
also have time to take a step back and
say okay like are we optimizing for the
right things what have we learned in the
last few weeks that either confirm or
deny the strategy were on is very
helpful all right and then the Third
phase and this is coming I don't know
how soon so maybe you can tip us off
when you think you'll be able to start
moving into this third phase but the
third phase being expansion so after you
start getting this premium product
dialed in what's the expansion plan from
there premium phase two as mentioned and
then phase three is expansion into
basically other platforms so we're only
iOS right now Android Mac desktop any
device that you may own or come across
maybe others Vision Pro and other in the
future because of course screen time
matters everywhere and also expansion in
terms of distribution where we currently
do e2c direct to Consumer we know that
we also have a B2B angle that we can
sell to colleges universities schools
but also employers and many others that
would be really phase three phase two
the goal is to work on this until end of
next year and then beyond that enter the
next phase of business you're working
backwards from what a lot of apps tend
to do like start start with flutter we
want to be on every platform from day
one we're going to launch iOS Android
web Mac you know whatever why did you
start iOS only I mean at 5 million AR
and not having an Android app is kind of
surprising compared to what we hear in
the industry oh you should be on Android
and so why did you do that and how's
that playing out it's working pretty
well there's just so much to do to
figure out the right kind of product and
the right kind of way to onboard people
that we felt it was better to do it on
oneform than multiple platforms but also
there's a timing thing where Apple
essentially introduced a screen time API
back in November last year I mean with
iOS 16 and we were the first app to
benefit from this API and to build on
this API so the focus was very clear
like there's an opportunity right now to
build on iOS and to build well I do
think that there is a lot of value in
being a crossplatform like just even Mac
plus iOS like if you work like me you
know with your iPhone and then also your
Mac there's natural extension there so
we're going to get there but you know
also quite resource constraints I mean
we just want to do what we can with the
resources we have but this will come
very soon yeah I think it can be a trap
for a lot of absolutely it's a trap it's
very resource intensive it's not linear
in platforms like two platforms is not
twox difficulty it's probably three or
fourx the difficulty and it's not 2x the
revenue yeah the ri is lower than the
first one and if you're still learning
in your core platform and like you're
still iterating those lessons not all of
them but a lot of them will translate to
your new thing and also like you're a
moving Target right now right this phase
of transitioning into premium may change
how the product looks and feels pretty
fundamentally potentially and like you
don't want to have to do that twice yeah
that's right do it once I mean you can
use tools and things like this but like
I do think that especially as you think
about word of mouth too like that's one
of the big reasons to have an Android
app is to make sure that every time
somebody says opal there's a listener on
the other end that can install it and
benefit and from what you've told us
from the mission obviously that's going
to have to happen but yeah for folks
like it can really be a trap don't feel
the pressure and this is why metrics are
important too cuz like if you don't have
a metric that's telling you like you're
not good enough yet you're G to be like
H maybe let's build an Android app
that's a good idea and you're G to waste
a bunch of time it's like no focus on
the RAS focus on whatever when you get
past a certain scale you'll have enough
threads and this is an interesting
transition point where you guys are at
seven people or 10 people is 20 30 40
once you get to 30 40 50 people then
it's like okay we can put four people on
an Android app and not derail the
company's progress right but at this
stage you have like one thing you can
think about as anization basically
that's so right I mean the other thing I
think depends I mean for us it's a
relatively new news case like people
don't have a screen time software on
their phones I think 25% of Americans
check their screen time stats others
don't so it's still pretty nent so
there's a lot of Discovery to figure out
like how do you build a product that
helps most people focus and so it's
easier in that Discovery phase to do on
one platform you're saying like when you
have two you kind of stuck the very
different user bases too right like I
mean eventually and this is I think
talking into that expansion and
distribution phase it's like you'll
build a brand that then you'll become
the ones educating the world on screen
time and that actually has an advantage
because when you go into those platforms
you already have this like body of brand
and experience and makes the conversion
much simpler I think absolutely that's
the plan I've also to back up what
you're saying Jacob I've seen like a lot
of horror stories from other startups
and actually end up like launching too
soon and when you ask them what's your
greatest gr they'll say well actually we
went on Android too soon or we went on
desktop or Chrome too soon and it's just
a version of the spreading yourself too
thin too fast we did it for years over
and over again until we really started
to understand like how much can we chew
at any given time but once you do and
that's the power loss right of
compounding as your company doubles or
doubles and doubles like one day you
wake up and you're like okay we actually
have a lot of capacity to like tackle
more than one thing and that's what you
should wait for right it's like wait so
it's all about being frenetic and fast
but also patient very difficult thing to
balance so we'll do a follow-up podcast
in the year will'll be be all over every
platform every screen speaking of
fenetic and fast you've been on my list
of people to invite to the podcast for a
while now but you tweeted recently
something that reminded me I gotta get
Kenneth on and that was you tweeted a
screenshot from notion with this massive
list of ab tests that You' run and then
somewhere in the Tweet you said we've
run 12 21 AB test so I wanted to spend
the rest of time digging into this
testing I mean that's a high velocity of
tests the first thing I want to ask is
what is your setup for testing like how
do you actually manage 121 test as a
small seven person team going from zero
to one it's a lot that's a lot I don't
advise everyone do as many I think we
probably could have avoided only do the
ones that work out yeah exactly save
half of them
big better no but we did do that I mean
I think one of the advantages of having
like a single metric that you look at in
this first phase which is the r it makes
it that much easier to AB test on a
single metric and as I was mentioning
earlier it's also like much shorter
iteration Cycles so if you run an AB
test you can get in our case because we
have a 7-Day free trial you probably get
most answers within eight days if you
have enough volume especially in early
days where you're looking for big
uplifts but our setup is I mean we use
Firebase for AB testing but we run off
tests through amplitude the data cohorts
data analysis through amplitude
basically with a user parameter on
amplitude for Baseline versus variance
and then we look at uplifts and figure
out statistical significance because we
AB tested a lot on day8 Ras it has a lot
to do with testing stuff very early in
the funnel the earliest in the funnel
the easiest it is to get statistical
significance quite fast let's talk
through we're going to have to kind of
speedrun these but we created a list of
your top three positive results and your
top three negative results so the first
one that you did that was a positive
result was showing the pay wall early so
tell me about that test like how you
executed it and then what the results
look like yeah it's almost like common
wisdom but it is true that we found we
tested many many iterations like where
to plays the onboarding where to plays
the pay wall what kind of pay wall how
easy is it to dismiss or not and when
you say how easy to dismiss you
mentioned that ear you mean like fading
in the X versus not or like full hard
payall or not it dance around when you
try to click on it that's right like
those old ads in 2002 we we didn't try
that one we probably
should it worked for Bonsai buddy I know
that no but we yeah definitely hiding or
making it as discreet as possible the
dismiss button for example was a winner
but I would say generally like what we
learned is you need to get the pay wall
to be as early as possible in the
onboarding but not too early and I think
what you're looking for is the peak
motivation moment where if you need a
few screens to build motivation and
build intent and then display the pay
wall that's better than like putting the
pay wall right away in the first screen
that's what we found at least so for
example for us what's interesting is you
download the app you might find out if
you do this you know we're GNA ask you
what's your screen time we're going to
ask you a few questions and then we're
going to build this mini report that
will one of the things it'll do is it'll
give you like a lifetime projection of
how much you're going to spend on your
phone and the average for a US person is
actually 22 years so you know
no
terrible so the average American gets a
smartphone age 12 77 year old is the
sort of average life expectancy and then
you spend five hours and eight minutes
on average which is if you look at only
wake hours because 16 hours awake during
the day basically adds up to a pretty
large portion of your day and then you
project that onto lifetime so anyway we
make that projection and then after we
make that projection we tell you hey but
the good news is we can save up to three
four five years of your life together
that's the moment where there's High
motivation and then people willing to
sign up to a free trial and a little bit
like a gym membership effects for sure
I'm going to commit to this and commit
to this change and the benefit of this
is you get people who of course pay but
also are quite motivated to try the
product and improve it and so yeah we I
think through various iterations we went
from about 7% of people who start a
trial to 177% of people who start a
trial from download be the number one
all right so the second one was on
boarding to a scheduled session this is
an interesting one yeah so what we found
is if you onboard people to committing
to something where they don't need to
remember later to do it like an
automatic action basically so for
example for us when you download the app
and you tell us which apps distract you
most so you might say like Instagram for
example or Tik Tok and then
automatically we're going to create this
Monday to Friday 9 to 5 work hour
schedule where when your work hours
start these apps will be blocked and so
what happens is you on board you might
like exit out of the app do something
else and then the next day you don't
need to remember it'll just start to
block the app and then you'll remember
oh I committed to this now I'm in that's
clearly something that was a huge win
for us yeah that's a really cool one we
talk a lot about retention and
onboarding and all these things on
podcast and yeah it's just such a
powerful thing to onboard to something
that's going to be right back in their
face soon it works for this and I think
also I add like one thing is so you
basically make it an automatic action
but you allow editing editing should be
very easy so like you make the
commitment but you can always come back
and like change it or cancel out of it
there's no problem but the default is
that you on board and then it just works
you don't need do anything else don't
don't dump somebody into an empty you
know like you should have an exact idea
of how you want the for every person's
experience to be and send everybody
right I used to describe onboarding it's
just like you want want people to slide
down into their first experience right
like no you don't want them to get
caught no bumpy elbows no nothing they
just click app launch and like they
don't do anything basically and then
then boom they land and they're figured
out right simultaneous to that you're
pitching them you're doing some other
things describing the value and the
thing is it's like you measured it it
actually helps and that's because that
first three minutes three to five
screens is so highly leveraged right
it's like every single dollar you're
spending on ads hits that every single
user has that experience they're going
to form an opinion about your ad
probably semi- permanently in that first
three to five minutes I sometimes see
people design tests super poorly so it's
not surprising to me that these are the
tests that you saw have really high
output because you want to test
something big and you want to test
something that's frequent right that
people see a lot what would you test
these against like were your variants
just like status quo then new idea is
that kind of how you evolve that you
know ideas to test yeah mostly just like
a binary test cuz we didn't have a ton
of volume sometimes we did variants
where like a different message or maybe
like a different placement they wall
position three versus bayall position
five that kind of thing but mostly
Baseline versus variant and then
adopting the winner and then like doing
it again the less extreme your test is
the longer it's going to take to get a
result or potentially not get a result
that's I think something unintuitive
about testing is that it's not just good
or bad most of the time it's
inconclusive and also the time it takes
to get conclusion is related to the
difference in the two right so if
they're identical the time it takes to
reach a conclusion about that is
actually pretty long so the bigger
swings you take the better yeah I will
say one thing so we didn't do well 121
is a lot but we could have done better
at prioritizing the bigger swings like
having a clear view what do you think
the uplift is likely to be and that's a
little bit like guess workor but I mean
you can come up with an estimation and
then priortize especially early like the
bigger swings if you get like a few
percentage points uplifts it's not going
to be enough you need massive uplifts at
the beginning sometimes it's a very
simple things like just putting the
payall to screens early two screens
before can be like plus 10% and trial
started and that's a massive win or
sometimes you can spend a lot of time to
build this new feature that will end up
moving things by a tiny piece I've done
that I've buil like long buildout
feature that has very little impact even
though it's beautiful right and it's
literally just changing the opacity to
the x button on the pay wall to 80%
increases Revenue 20% you're like okay
why do I even try and it's sounding also
to stay motivated now when you've done
these tests for the team like you work
five weeks on something or 3 weeks on
something and then changes nothing or it
changes like 1% but yeah I think
definitely testing is you have to be in
the spirit of a lot of things will fail
I think those failures are good though
because I think it teaches you reality I
think too many people have some sort of
like magical thinking about how
everybody's Steve Jobs and if they just
apply their big brain product brain and
think of the perfect thing and then they
make it look beautiful and they ship it
it's going to matter and sometimes that
is true but I think most people have a
unrealistic understanding of how the
world works and like AB testing is a
really good way of kind of putting your
nose in it
and being like nope nobody cares or
maybe they do but I think the sooner you
get over that as a product Builder and
that's all levels right you were saying
it's like the engineers being
demotivated and even the folks coming up
with ideas it's like teaching them where
are the levers of change on our product
that's a thing I think a team because
once you've got it baked into the
culture of your team two years from now
or a year from now and some bright-eyed
new product manager coming in they're
like what if we they're like no like we
did this test number 63 total failure
which you know may or may not be useful
but that understanding of the physics of
your business and what moves the needle
and what doesn't I think that's I mean
Facebook was really good at this that's
what drove them you know they just
learned like connections like that's
everything and goes back to this one
simplified metrics and then also the
iteration Cycles you guys there's no way
you did 121 test if you weren't shipping
every week right that would be
impossible definitely and so you have to
also pick a metric that allows you to do
that but that's helpful I mean another
interesting example is tiered referral
rewards so basically we have in the app
you can invite people and if you invite
five people you get the subscription for
free like for a year that's kind of like
an organic mechanism but one very small
change that we did is we basically
mostly like make it look better this
referral program and then like have a
tiered reward system where like you
invite five people get the free year you
invite like 20 you get a lifetime sub
you get a special prize at 50 and kind
of like putting that into a beautiful UI
that just like gives people a goal of
how to invite people and that led to 80%
Improvement in how many people send the
referral to at least one person it's
really interesting to think about how
because that's a very different user
that you're trying to optimize around
than the person who's buying the $100
annual subscription during onboarding
that's the kind of thing you're going to
have to figure out as you it sounds like
you already have started to figure out
like okay make sure that you're coming
in are you 25 to 35 professional okay
you're going to go down this way are you
17 to 22 you're GNA go down the referral
program actually we do that and I would
actually advise everyone to do this as
well like you just ask people their age
and different CH on
boarding yeah yeah yeah yeah that makes
sense all right so tiered referrals was
the third positive result but we got to
speedrun the top three negative results
and to Jacob's point this platonic ideal
of like we're going to run this test and
it's always going to be meaningful but
it's meaningful whether it's a positive
or A negative result and usually want
more negative results so tell me about
the top three negative or we'll go one
by one but what's the first negative
result that was meaningful because you
learned so much sure I mean we failed a
lot for sure um so these are the top
three most meaningful negative results
but the first one it's very hard to beat
the blinkist pay wall so I don't know if
you know the blinkist kind of pay wall I
mean it was published and I think in the
mobile app sub Community it's probably a
very well-known fact but basically this
transparent payall that shows you hey
you're going to start the tree trial now
and then like in six days you get a
reminder and in seven days you'll pay
your for subscription it kind of like
decreases the anxiety of people to sign
up to a free trial so we have that and
that's the main pay wall right now in
the on boarding and we tried dozens of
others and actually keep trying but
we've never been that pay wall so a lot
of failure around that placement though
you seem to have tested well but the
actual content it's not a huge lever
yeah that makes sense the content hasn't
been that huge of a lever I mean we did
experiment to get to that blink Pall but
once we've had it so far we haven't made
gains too much choice in the onboarding
is another one so we tried in a few
different ways offering people a choice
on how to disconnect so you I mentioned
earlier that the default way right now
is work hours 9 to 5 Monday Friday we're
going to block all distracting apps and
then you can go back and edit and choose
no I don't want work hours want
something else whenever we tried to give
people more choice in the onboarding it
failed and that's a little bit to your
point Jacob of like you want the
smoothest got to be slick yeah there's
limited fatigue budget users only going
going to make so many choices and you
need to make sure you're spending that
mental energy on exactly the things you
have to people live very busy lives and
their onboarding they might be doing
something else they need something very
simple to commit to that was meaningful
in the sense that we know now that the
automatic action is really the best way
to do this and we're still experimenting
around this but this is a clear one and
then yeah the other thing is we've done
a lot of tests that didn't work on
re-engaging people after the initial on
boarding in the first day and a lot of
it failed with one notable exception
I'll say like when people cancel their
trial We re-engage Them of an offer and
that works quite well it's really
interesting that they're non-committed
enough to be like no I'm not paying for
this but then you present them with a
deal and everybody's like well I did get
a deal like I almost wonder how much of
it is that it's like well I better take
advantage of well who cares right you
don't need to know why so how would you
do that but you would detect the trial
cancellation via revenue cat.com and
then you would just fire an email
because you have their email or a push
notification or what was we actually do
so we do use Revenue cats by the way
this is not an ad
um it is an ad don't let them confuse
you so we do use Revenue cat for
subscription status we actually use a
software called one signal great
software currently we send notifications
with a 50% off offer actually right now
but it's being AB tested you might not
get this offer you might get a different
one this is this is yeah don't call
kenth do this somebody's going to send
you a nasty email at opal I heard on the
podcast that I could get % off this is
not legally binding and then also in app
kind of modal when you come back say Hey
you know okay so yeah making sure you
get the visibility on it but it's
interesting that you're doing it very
much targeted in the app experience
right which probably makes the most
sense it's people have the context and
all that well I think emails can work
too we used to collect them we don't
anymore as part of the onboarding
process we have a phone number sign in
and imagine that was an AB test that
collecting the email caus more drop off
still to be determined but basically we
have a social feature inside the app
where you can see your friend screen
time which I find is very cool speaking
about the ideas that might not turn out
into yeah I don't care about other
people's screen time but I think if I
showed people my screen time I think it
would make me better about it right like
that's got to be the idea yeah there's
all this thing about positive peer
pressure in the sense like there's sure
it's
positive well you know in like addiction
science you know AA and others the
support group that you get of people
that are like supportive but also kind
of checking in I'm like what are you
doing can help and so that's the idea
but so far it has been AB tested it was
a slight uplift we do get people that
invite their friends but it's not in the
three most meaningful wins so far but
we're still working on various ideas to
essentially focus better with your
friends in different ways and have a
support group and so the phone number
bur authentication kind of allows for
that I think that's a great place to
wrap up21 AB tests a lot of failure how
many are you doing in 2024 200 you know
it's exponential it's like the
AR good thousand you're doing something
right all right it was so much fun
talking to you Kenneth thanks for being
on the podcast yeah thanks so much for
the invite David and Jacob and congrats
on Revan cats amazing software so
excited to be using it every day oh geez
thank you but I do want my t-shirts
please okay I'll get your T-shirt don't
worry
thanks thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
in your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private
[Music]
community